{"tossups": [{"question": "Supporters of this legislation organized the \u201cPrison Special\u201d in which members of the Silent Sentinels traveled from city to city giving speeches. In a speech supporting this legislation, Woodrow Wilson asked if a certain group should only have \u201csuffering and sacrifice\u201d without \u201cprivilege and right.\u201d Carrie Chapman Catt and Alice Paul rallied the NAWSA in support of this amendment. For ten points, name this amendment that gave women the right to vote.", "answer": "<b> 19</b>th Amendment", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A president of this country tried to avoid the ramifications of the Rywingate corruption scandal by claiming parliamentary commissions couldn\u2019t investigate him. The President of the European Council, Donald Tusk, was Prime Minister of this country during the early 2010s. A trade union founded in this country\u2019s Lenin Shipyards in 1980 was led by electrician and future President Lech Walesa [lek vah-WEN-sah]. For ten points, name this eastern European country where Solidarity rose to power in Warsaw.", "answer": "<b> Poland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A character in this novel declares a wish to become a vivandi`ere in the Union Army to join her father, Robert, before he is wounded in 1862. John Brooke is also wounded in the Civil War and, with one of this novel\u2019s title characters, becomes the father of twins Daisy and Demi. Professor Bhaer and Laurie Laurence marry two of the other March sisters in, for ten points, what novel by Louisa May Alcott about Meg, Jo, Beth, and Amy?", "answer": "<b> Little Women</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "A territory governed by this country contains the island of Saipan and is governed from the town of Capitol Hill. UN Security Council Resolution 21 gave this country the Northern Mariana Islands. During the Spanish Flu epidemic, John Martin Poyer quarantined an island territory of this country and its bay at Pago Pago. A portion of Samoa is governed by, for ten points, what country whose Pacific holdings also include Guam and Hawaii?", "answer": "<b> United States</b> of America (or<b> America</b>; accept<b> US</b>A)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s presidency, the Insanity Defense Reform Act shifted the burden of proof for insanity defenses from the prosecution to the defense. This man\u2019s press secretary, James Brady, received wounds that contributed to his death 33 years later when, due to his fixation on Jodie Foster, John Hinckley Jr. fired six shots at this man. For ten points, name this Republican President who was the target of an assassination attempt in 1981.", "answer": "Ronald<b> Reagan</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event\u2019s scoring reform in 2016 allowed participating countries to score twice as many \u201cdouze points\u201d [dooz pwant] as before. This event was created in 1956 as an effort to popularize live TV throughout Western Europe. Australia is a guest competitor in, for ten points, what annual international song competition that was won in 2019 by the Netherlands?", "answer": "<b> Eurovision</b> Song Contest", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In this country, a 90-day state of emergency edict was continually renewed by Alfred Stroessner for over 30 years. This country\u2019s leader, Francisco Solano Lopez, died at the Battle of Cerro Cor\u00b4a near the end of the War of the Triple Alliance. This country defended the nearby Republic of Uruguay after it was invaded by Pedro II. For ten points, name this country where Brazilian forces occupied Asuncio\u00b4n at the end of a 1864 war.", "answer": "<b> Paraguay</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This woman was abducted after being tricked into boarding Samuel Argall\u2019s ship. Alexander Whitaker converted this woman to Christianity and oversaw her baptism, upon which she took the name Rebecca. With Tomocomo, this woman traveled to England with her husband John Rolfe. This daughter of Powhatan legendarily stopped the execution of an English colonist by placing her head over his body. For ten points, name this Native American woman who may have saved John Smith.", "answer": "<b> Pocahontas</b> (accept Rebecca<b> Rolfe</b> before \u201cRolfe\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An ominous message reading this man \u201cwill die and his land will be divided\u201d was written on a fallen meteor in Dongjun. Gao Jianli attempted to assassinate this man with a lute. This man, aided by Li Si, unified his country\u2019s writing system. During this man\u2019s rule, he carried out the \u201cburning of the books and burying of the scholars\u201d to promote legalism. The Warring States period was ended by, for ten points, what first Emperor of China?", "answer": "Qin<b> Shi Huang</b>di (accept<b> Zhao Zheng</b>; accept<b> Ying Zheng</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This scientist names a law that relates the product of two masses with the inverse square of the distance separating them. This thinker\u2019s essay<em> General Scholium</em>, which included the quotation \u201cHypotheses non fingo,\u201d was an addendum to his<em> Principia</em>. Independent of Gottfried Leibniz, this scientist invented calculus. For ten points, name this scientist whose laws of inertia, acceleration, and action and reaction form the three laws of motion.", "answer": "Sir Isaac<b> Newton</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "Claudius Gothicus died during one of these events named for Cyprian. A diplomatic mission to China may have caused one of these events that likely claimed the life of Lucius Verus. Over 5 million people may have died in an event of this type that began under, and is named for, Antoninus Pius. Galen observed that fevers and boils were common symptoms of one of these events. For ten points, name these events, massive outbreaks of disease.", "answer": "<b> plague</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "The settlement house movement sought to help people facing this condition by introducing them to middle class values. In<em> Nickel and Dimed</em>, Barbara Ehrenreich examined this condition among employed people. This condition is defined as having an income less than three times the average food budget in the United States, while the extreme form of this condition is often identified as living on less than a dollar a day. For ten points, name this condition characterized by a lack of money.", "answer": "<b> poverty</b> (accept obvious equivalents such as being<b> poor</b> or<b> material hardship</b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Daniel F. O\u2019Leary refused to obey this man\u2019s orders to burn his personal letters after his death. Manuela Saenz protected this man from an assassination attempt after winning</b> <b>the Battle of Pichincha. The (+)</b> <b>Decree of War to the Death was passed by this man to</b> <b>punish those who helped enemy forces during his (*)</b> Admirable Campaign. The first President of Gran Colombia was, for ten points, what \u201cliberator\u201d of South America who is honored as the namesake of a country with capitals Sucre and La Paz?", "answer": "Simon<b> Bolivar</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In one story, Vishnu warns Manu of one of these events known as the</b><em><b> pralaya</b></em><b>, a word that translates to \u201cdissolution.\u201d In the Epic of Gilgamesh, Utnapishtim and his wife are the (+) sole survivors of one of these disasters. A man survives another one of these events with</b> <b>his sons Shem, Ham and Japheth, eventually (*)</b> landing on Mount Ararat. Historical theories have been developed to explain why various cultures have a myth about, for ten points, what type of disaster that, in the Book of Genesis, wipes out most of humanity, except those aboard Noah\u2019s ark?", "answer": "mythical<b> flood</b>s (or<b> deluge</b>s)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b>This artist, who painted a yellow bedframe in his blue</b><em><b> Bedroom at Arles</b></em><b>, failed to sell most of his still-lives of roses, irises and sunflowers during his lifetime. Self-portraits with a straw hat and (+) bandage were painted by this man, whose most famous work was created</b> <b>while institutionalized in Saint-R\u00b4emy. Cypress (*)</b> trees rise up into a swirled blue and yellow evening sky in a work by, for ten points, what Dutch artist of<em> The Starry Night</em> who famously cut off his own ear?", "answer": "Vincent Willem<b> van Gogh</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>In the aftermath of this battle, captured soldiers formed the Convention Army. Timothy</b> <b>Murphy may have killed Simon (+)</b> <b>Fraser at this battle on the orders of Daniel Morgan.</b> <b>The American victory at this battle ended a campaign to secure the (*)</b> Hudson River Valley led by John Burgoyne. Horatio Gates and Benedict Arnold led American troops in, for ten points, what decisive 1777 battle that convinced the French to join the Revolutionary War?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Saratoga</b> (accept Battle of<b> Freeman\u2019s Farm</b>; accept Battle of<b> Bemis Heights</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A leader of this city, Cleombrotus I, was killed at the 371 BC Battle of Leuctra. A fleet</b> <b>from this city, under the command of (+)</b> <b>Lysander, won the Battle of Aegospotami near</b> <b>the end of the Peloponnesian War. In this city, Cinadon attempted to overthrow the (*) </b>Eurypontid King Agesilaus II with the help of the helots. Three hundred soldiers from this city fought a valiant battle against invading Persian forces at the Battle of Thermopylae. Leonidas led, for ten points, what Greek city-state, the arch-rival to Athens?", "answer": "<b> Sparta</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This ruler founded a secret police represented by an emblem with a broom and a dog\u2019s head. With the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth, this man agreed to the Truce of Yam-Zapolsky to help end the (+) Livonian War. Boyars who opposed this ruler were hunted down by the oprichiniki. According to legend, this man blinded the architect of (*)</b> Saint Basil\u2019s Cathedral. Feodor I succeeded this ruler, whose death sparked the Time of Troubles. For ten points, name this Tsar of Russia known for his brutality.", "answer": "<b> Ivan IV</b> (accept<b> Ivan the Terrible</b>; accept<b> Ivan Grozny</b>; prompt on Ivan)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}